FILE: PSAD.pm

LABEL: psad_config
SHORT_EXP: "Bastille provides the option to configure psad (the Port Scan Attack
Detector), which analyzes information gathered in firewall logs to determine whether
or not someone is scanning your machine.  Psad features a set of flexible thresholds
(with sensible defaults provided) that are used to define what constitutes a port
scan, detection for advanced port scans (syn, fin, Xmas) that are easily leveraged
against a machine via nmap, email alerts that contain the source and destination ip
addresses, the range of scanned ports, begin and end times, tcp flags set in the
scanning packets, reverse dns and whois information, DShield alerting, passive OS
fingerprinting, auto-blocking of scanning ip addresses (disabled by default), and
more.  In addition psad incorporates many of the tcp, udp, and icmp rules included
in the snort intrusion detection system to detect probes for back-door and DDoS
programs.

*** psad must be installed before the Bastille can configure it, but if you
answer the following questions you can have Bastille apply your configuration
after installing psad.  The latest version of psad can be downloaded from
http://www.cipherdyne.org/psad/

NOTE: For psad to be effective, it is required that the firewall is active."
QUESTION: "Would you like to setup psad?"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
YN_TOGGLE: 1
REG_EXP: "^Y$|^N$"
DEFAULT_ANSWER: N
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_check_interval
SKIP_CHILD: End_Screen
NO_CHILD: End_Screen
SKIP_CHILD: End_Screen
PROPER_PARENT: ip_advnetwork

LABEL: psad_check_interval
SHORT_EXP: "This controls how often psad checks for packet that have been denied by
the firewall. A good default is 15 seconds.

It is important to not set this value too high because psad alerts are sent when the
interval ends and it is important to determine when your machine is being scanned as
quickly as possible.  Also, setting the value too low can make psad quickly generate
alerts and utilize much of your systems resources if your machine is subjected to a
high-traffic scan."
QUESTION: "psad check interval: [15]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
DEFAULT_ANSWER: 15
CONFIRM_TEXT: " \nY"
YN_TOGGLE: 0
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_port_range_scan_threshold
NO_CHILD: psad_port_range_scan_threshold
PROPER_PARENT: psad_config

LABEL: psad_port_range_scan_threshold
SHORT_EXP: "Psad has been designed to allow the administrator to define what network
traffic constitutes a port scan. This value determines a minimum range of ports that
must be scanned from interval to interval before an alert will be sent.  For example,
if this value is set to 0, psad will consider that multiple packets to the same port
qualify as a port scan. However if this value is set to 10 then there must be a
difference of 10 ports in a scan before psad considers it as such.

The default is 1 which means that unless at least two ports are scanned psad will
ignore the traffic. This also implies that multiple packets sent to the same port do
not qualify as a port scan."
QUESTION: "Port range scan threshold: [1]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
DEFAULT_ANSWER: 1
CONFIRM_TEXT: " \nY"
YN_TOGGLE: 0
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_enable_persistence
NO_CHILD: psad_enable_persistence
PROPER_PARENT: psad_check_interval

LABEL: psad_enable_persistence
SHORT_EXP: "Detecting port scans is all about setting thresholds for the number of
ports scanned within a fixed period of time. Hence, an attacker can try to slip beneath
the threshold by using a long time interval (hours or even days) between scanning each
port on a target machine. Setting this value to Y will configure psad to keep a
summary of all scanned ports indefinitely within memory for each ip so that port scans
do not expire over time.

The default is N since most scans are easily recognizable within a short time interval
which is configured in the next question box if you leave this value as N."
QUESTION: "Enable scan persistence?"
REQUIRE_DISTRO:  LINUX
YN_TOGGLE: 1
REG_EXP: "^Y$|^N$"
DEFAULT_ANSWER: N
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_show_all_signatures
NO_CHILD: psad_scan_timeout
SKIP_CHILD: psad_scan_timeout
PROPER_PARENT: psad_port_range_scan_threshold

LABEL: psad_scan_timeout
SHORT_EXP: "This will allow you to define the length of time psad considers data about
a port scan or potential port scan to be important. If this length of time passes after
an initial port scan is detected, the ip from which the scan originated is purged from
psad's memory space along with the scan data.

The default is 3600 seconds (one hour)."
QUESTION: "Scan timeout: [3600]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
DEFAULT_ANSWER: 3600
CONFIRM_TEXT: " \nY"
YN_TOGGLE: 0
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_show_all_signatures
NO_CHILD: psad_show_all_signatures
PROPER_PARENT: psad_enable_persistence

LABEL: psad_show_all_signatures
SHORT_EXP: "Psad makes use of many tcp and udp signatures included within the snort
intrusion detection system to detect scans for various back doors and/or trojans (Back
Orifice, SubSeven, etc.), DDoS tools (mstream, shaft) and advanced port scans (SYN,
FIN, XMAS, NULL). Over the course of a scan psad keeps track of all signatures that
have been matched and if this value is set to Y, all matched signatures will be
printed with every alert email instead of just the most recently matched ones.

The default is N since the email record will already contain just the most recently
matched signatures."
QUESTION: "Show all scan signatures?"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
YN_TOGGLE: 1
REG_EXP: "^Y$|^N$"
DEFAULT_ANSWER: N
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_danger_levels
NO_CHILD: psad_danger_levels
PROPER_PARENT: psad_scan_timeout

LABEL: psad_danger_levels
SHORT_EXP: "As port scans are detected by psad they are assigned a danger level from
1 to 5 based on the number of packets and whether they match a specific signature
(iptables only).

The default number of packets for each danger level are as follows:
Danger Level 1 = 5 packets
Danger Level 2 = 50 packets
Danger Level 3 = 1000 packets
Danger Level 4 = 5000 packets
Danger Level 5 = 10000 packets"
QUESTION: "Danger Levels: [5 50 1000 5000 10000]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
DEFAULT_ANSWER: 5 50 1000 5000 10000
YN_TOGGLE: 0
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_email_alert_addresses
NO_CHILD: psad_email_alert_addresses
PROPER_PARENT: psad_show_all_signatures

LABEL: psad_email_alert_addresses
SHORT_EXP: "Psad supports sending email alerts to multiple email addresses. You can
specify as many email addresses as you like; just enter them one right after another
without any commas.

The default email address is root@localhost."
QUESTION: "Email addresses: [root@localhost]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
DEFAULT_ANSWER: root@localhost
YN_TOGGLE: 0
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_email_alert_danger_level
NO_CHILD: psad_email_alert_danger_level
PROPER_PARENT: psad_danger_levels

LABEL: psad_email_alert_danger_level
SHORT_EXP: "Psad can be configured to send an email alert for a scan only after the
scan has reached a certain danger level. For example, if you don't want psad to alert
you about a scan until it has reached the highest danger level (5), then you would set
this value to 5.

The default danger level is 1."
QUESTION: "Email alert danger level: [1]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
DEFAULT_ANSWER: 1
YN_TOGGLE: 0
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_alert_all
NO_CHILD: psad_alert_all
PROPER_PARENT: psad_email_alert_addresses

LABEL: psad_alert_all
SHORT_EXP: "Throughout the course of a scan, new packets may be sent to your machine
that don't trip the next danger threshold and hence psad will not alert you unless
the value is set to Y.

The default is Y since once a scan reaches the threshold assigned in the previous
section you will probably want as much information on it as psad can produce."
QUESTION: "Alert on all new packets?"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
YN_TOGGLE: 1
REG_EXP: "^Y$|^N$"
DEFAULT_ANSWER: Y
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_enable_auto_ids
NO_CHILD: psad_enable_auto_ids
PROPER_PARENT: psad_email_alert_danger_level

LABEL: psad_enable_auto_ids
SHORT_EXP: "Psad has the capability of automatically blocking any IP address that
has scanned your machine if the scan trips a certain threshold. WARNING: This feature
has the potential to create the ability for anyone to commit a Denial of Service
against your machine/network and cause psad to block all access to any website of the
attacker's choosing. For example, suppose that an attacker wants to make psad block
access to www.yahoo.com. Then all the attacker would need to do is spoof a port scan
from www.yahoo.com's IP address(es) and make sure the scan is comprehensive enough to
trip the automatic blocking threshold.

The default is N for the reason given above, but if the requirements for your site
outweigh this possibility then answering Y will enable the automatic blocking
feature and the next section will ask you to define a corresponding danger
threshold."
QUESTION: "Enable automatic blocking of scanning IPs?"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
YN_TOGGLE: 1
REG_EXP: "^Y$|^N$"
DEFAULT_ANSWER: N
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_auto_ids_danger_level
NO_CHILD: psad_enable_at_boot
SKIP_CHILD: psad_enable_at_boot
PROPER_PARENT: psad_alert_all

LABEL: psad_auto_ids_danger_level
SHORT_EXP: "This controls at what danger level a scan must reach before it is
automatically blocked by psad. Normally this value should be set to a relatively high
value so that only IP addresses that leverage really comprehensive scans will be
blocked.

The default danger level is 5."
QUESTION: "Auto blocking danger level: [5]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
DEFAULT_ANSWER: 5
YN_TOGGLE: 0
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
YES_CHILD: psad_enable_at_boot
NO_CHILD: psad_enable_at_boot
PROPER_PARENT: psad_enable_auto_ids

LABEL: psad_enable_at_boot
SHORT_EXP: "The Port Scan Attack Detector is controlled by a standard Sys V style
init script, /etc/rc.d/init.d/psad.  To start the psad daemons, simply execute
        /etc/rc.d/init.d/psad start
and to stop psad, execute
        /etc/rc.d/init.d/psad stop

Bastille can configure your system to start psad at boot time by executing
        chkconfig psad on."
QUESTION: "Should Bastille enable psad at boot time? [N]"
REQUIRE_DISTRO: LINUX
YN_TOGGLE: 1
REG_EXP: "^Y$|^N$"
YES_EXP:
NO_EXP:
DEFAULT_ANSWER: N
YES_CHILD: End_Screen
NO_CHILD: End_Screen
PROPER_PARENT: psad_enable_auto_ids


